<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An appeale to truth, in the controuersie betweene art, &amp; vse about the best and most expedient course in languages. To be read fasting; for the greater benefit of the deluded innocencie of our owne, and other nations. Drawen, and exhibited, by Ios. Webbe, Dr. of Ph.</title>
            <author>Webbe, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119583</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854790</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854790</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20234</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14865)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20234)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1015:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An appeale to truth, in the controuersie betweene art, &amp; vse about the best and most expedient course in languages. To be read fasting; for the greater benefit of the deluded innocencie of our owne, and other nations. Drawen, and exhibited, by Ios. Webbe, Dr. of Ph.</title>
                  <author>Webbe, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 52, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H[umphrey] L[ownes] for George Latham: and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Brazen Serpent,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An appeale to truth, concerning art and vse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Language and languages --  Study and teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Latin language --  Study and teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20234:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20234:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APPEALE to Truth, <hi>Jn the Controuerſie betweene</hi> ART, &amp; VSE; About the beſt and moſt expedient Courſe <hi>in</hi> LANGVAGES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To be read Faſting;</hi> For the greater benefit of the deluded innocencie of our owne, and other Nations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Drawen, and Exhibited,</hi> by IOS. WEBBE, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>of</hi> Ph.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Non fumum ex fulgore, ſed ex fumo dare lucem</l>
               <l>Cogitat: vt ſpecioſa dehinc miracula promat.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Hor.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>George Latham:</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Brazen Serpent, 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20234:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20234:2"/>
            <head>Great LADY, and ſole GOVERNESSE of my <hi>beſt Endeuours:</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing a purpoſe to divulge an vnattempted Courſe whereby deſired Languages may in their natiue puritie, and vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed perfection be archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: and finding Opinion (taken on Truſt, rather then grounded on due examination) to be the maine impediment in my proceedings; I thought it vſefull partly by reaſon, partly by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, but eſpecially by ancient, weightie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain'd <hi>Authoritie,</hi> to reclaime it; And by this <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale</hi> to referre all vnto the cenſure of thy moſt iuſt, and vncorrupt vprightnes.</p>
            <p>Thou knoweſt <hi>(O Truth)</hi> that <hi>Grammar</hi> (an Art whereby Languages are now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly held to be ſufficiently taught in euery Nation) was not in vſe amongſt the antient <hi>Romanes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tranquillut. Th. zuing. l.</hi> 1.</note> much leſſe in any reputation. And when it had acceſſe vnto their children, it was at the firſt full of humilitie; and tooke vpon it no more than the name <hi>Grammatica</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:20234:3"/>(tranſlated
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quint. de Inſt. Or. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>literatura</hi> or
<note n="b" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Gill Logon. cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>literatoria</hi>) could well war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: which was (not to teach the language; for that was their owne alreadie, but) to
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lud. Viu. de cauſ. corr. Ar. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; Com. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;. c.</hi> 5.</note> teach the letters, ſyllables and words (therof) and how to pronounce, write, and place them rightly (not according to any mans new found precepts, but) after aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent receiued <hi>Cuſtome;</hi> leſt with
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Philoſt. in Soph. et vol.</hi> 18. <hi>vrb. com. Zuin. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> they might confound the letters, and make of long ſhort, and of ſhort long ſyllables: Or fall vpon an euill pronunciation (which
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ob. ſer.</hi> 2. <hi>de imprudentia.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theocritus</hi> ſo prettily reprehended in a <hi>Grammarian.</hi>) Or tranſpoſe words (which was ſo hatefull to <hi>Pomponius Marcellus;</hi> that
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tranquillus. Zuing. Th. l.</hi> 1.</note> in the height of his pleading, he (like a wiſe <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marian</hi>) left and loſt his Cauſe, to fall vpon his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries tranſpoſition.) Or leſt words might bee vſed which were not Latine (for which
<note n="g" place="margin">Id. ib.</note> 
               <hi>Tiberius Caeſar</hi> was accuſed by the ſame <hi>Pomponius.</hi>) Or leſt words, and languages might be abuſed by a rude, and externe ignorance: as
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Annalium l.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Auentinus</hi> reports of that <hi>Bauarian</hi> who baptiz'd a boy, <hi>In nomine Patria, filia, et Spiritus ſancta.</hi> And in this nature, ſuch as teach to read and write by th' <hi>A. B. C.</hi> Primers, horne bookes, and the like, may be truly ſaid to teach the Grammar:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quint. Inſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> for theſe were the vttermoſt limits of the firſt <hi>Grammarians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which <hi>Plato's Socrates</hi> makes manifeſt as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.
<note place="margin">In Philebo.</note> After Voice was thought (ſaith he) to be infinite, ſome <hi>God,</hi> or diuine <hi>Man</hi> (as that <hi>Thenth</hi> was reported to haue been amongſt th' <hi>Aegyptians</hi>) conſidered this in that infinite generalitie, the firſt letters were vocall; and that they were of more
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20234:3"/>than one ſort. And, further, that there were other which did not partake of the voice, but of the ſound: And hee alſo reduced them into a certaine number. Then, he diſtinguiſhed a third ſort of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters now called Mutes. Laſt of all, he diſtributed thoſe that were without ſound, and Mutes, euen to certaine particulars. So did hee with thoſe that were vocal, and halfe vocal; till he had found out their number, as well in part, as in whole, and called them <hi>Elements.</hi> And when he had wel weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that none of vs could euer gather any thing of theſe in particular, vnleſſe we knew them all, and had conſidered that all made but one kinde of knot, and was but a reduction of diſperſed things togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that in theſe he had found out there was an Art; he call'd it <hi>Grammar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, this little creeping fountaine,
<note place="margin">Quint. ib.</note> hauing in time, through continuall, and vniuerſall imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, gotten credit, wealth, and patronage, grew ambitious; and vnder the firſt title of intire ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, hath at length engroſſed riuers, ſtreames,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lud. Viu. de cauſis corr. Art. l.</hi> 2.</note> and branches, out of <hi>Orators, Poets,</hi> and <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> yea and almoſt all the greateſt artes, and ſciences; and is become a full-ſwolne, and ouer-flowing Sea, which by a ſtrong hand arrogates vnto it ſelfe (and hath well neere gotten) the whole traffick in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but eſpecially for languages.</p>
            <p>And though it be herein iudged by <hi>Quintilian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> and other antient Authors, to haue vſurped the function and the right of others: yet imboldned by partiall fauour, and a trick of it owne inuention,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20234:4"/>call'd <hi>Synecdoche,</hi> it dares without bluſhing tearm it ſelfe by that former poore, and ſillie name, <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Arte (or Science,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Cauſis Ling. Lat. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> as <hi>Iul. Scaliger</hi> would haue it) in it owne circuit &amp; firſt humilitie, is to be reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced for th' antiquitie, &amp; for the place &amp; prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence thereof amongſt the liberall Arts, or Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Com. l.</hi> 2</note> (though neither it, nor any of the reſt can teach the languages.) But, as it is ambitious, and aſſumeth to it ſelfe the right of others, promiſing that which it performeth not; ſo is it warily to be lookt into: leaſt (as hitherto) it trifle awaie our time, conſume our exhibitions, fruſtrate our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, diſinable our ſelues, and wrong the ends of our intentions. For, neither hath the name propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the thing, nor the thing with what it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth.</p>
            <p>Which being at the laſt iudiciouſly conſidered by a diligent and able <hi>Grammarian,</hi> appointed (doubtleſſe) to be the firſt who ſhould begin to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrate betwene the lawfull owner, and this bould intruder; hee hath ominouſly diſpoſſeſſed ould and toothleſſe <hi>Grammatica,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 18.</note> and conferr'd the art of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and of ſpeaking rightly, vpon a more deſeruing heire, <hi>Logonomia.</hi> Which, as it comprehends the whole ſpeach of a Nation, ſo the Author meaneth it ſhal include al things neceſſarie to their language; as, <hi>Grammar, Etymologie, Syntax, Proſodie, Logick, Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, Oratorie,</hi> and what elſe ſoeuer. Otherwiſe, this name ſhould not imbrace what the ſpeech of a Nation comprehendeth; nor ſhould th' Inuenter
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20234:4"/>haue ſo full and reuerent an opinion thereof as it behoueth.</p>
            <p>But (to goe a little further than the name) had this vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding Maſter (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he diſpoſſeſt the one, and inueſted the other) altered the crazy tenure by which <hi>Grammatica</hi> formerly held the principalitie of writing and of ſpeaking rightly (making that which was vſurped by the tenure of Art, rule, and precept, to be more ſurely houlden vnder vſe, cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, and authoritie) all nations had beene happie in his iuſt arbitrement. Yet howſoeuer, I ſhall die contented, to haue but ſeene this onely name thus altered. For, in this caſe had Truth com ruſhing all at once amidſt her enemies and ill-willers, it might haue imported daunger to her perſon: but as it is, I may liue in hope, that by that time this new name be well digeſted, th' oulde tenure wil be ſome-what altered.</p>
            <p>For, if we open the right eye, the eye of <hi>Equitie;</hi> &amp; wink with the left of <hi>Partialitie,</hi> and aime only at the publick good of our Nation &amp; poſteritie, and ſpeake what we apprehend ingenuouſly; wee ſhall be forced, by that which followeth, to confeſſe, that this Art neuer was or can be perfected; and that of ſuch as pretend pure languages it ought in no caſe to be followed.</p>
            <p>The truth whereof ſhall appeare aſwell by the diſsenſion of her chiefeſt vphoulders and the beſt <hi>Grammarians;</hi> as by their accuſation produced from authentick <hi>Orators, Hiſtorians, Poets,</hi> and <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20234:5"/>
            <p> For,
<note place="margin">In Ep. ad Reſt. &amp; alibi.</note> 
               <hi>Cominius</hi> tels vs, that the beſt <hi>Grammarians</hi> haue from Age to Age ſucceſſiuely quoted the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and errors of each other.
<note place="margin">Grammarians diſſenting.</note> 
               <hi>Donatus, Seruius,</hi> and <hi>Priſcianus,</hi> accuſed their predeceſſors; and were afterwards themſelues taxed by <hi>Beroaldus, Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus, Philelphus,</hi> and <hi>Laurentius Valla:</hi> and theſe, by <hi>Baptiſta Pius, Georgius</hi> and <hi>Petrus Valla, Aldus Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus, Perottus Sipuntinus,</hi> &amp;c: and theſe, by <hi>Pylades Brixianus;</hi> and hee, and the former by <hi>Quintianus Stoa:</hi> and <hi>Stoa,</hi> by <hi>Phineus, Domitius</hi> and others: and to come to our owne times, <hi>Martinus Cruſius</hi> was inuay'd againſt by <hi>Friſchlinus;</hi> and our Engliſh <hi>Lilie</hi> by the Spaniſh <hi>Aluarus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ralph Git<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins.</hi>
               </note> and, as I heare, by a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of our owne Nation, who brings him on the ſtage for many errors.</p>
            <p>Some of theſe call the reſt <hi>Grammatiſtae,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stoa in arte verſif. Suetonius. Zuing. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Th.</hi>
                  </note> ſeu litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores; Grammaticuli; Grammatociphones;</hi> and by other names of ignorance; as, <hi>incurioſi,</hi> and <hi>Scioli:</hi> yea, and ſome of them tell their companions, that their works, and precepts are tedious; and that they are not able to vtter their owne name in good latine; as <hi>Valla</hi> tels <hi>Priſcianus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> c.</hi> 1. <hi>Com. in Ep.</hi>
               </note> And this <hi>Valla</hi> tels others, that they vnteach the latine tongue. But, <hi>Pius Bononienſis</hi> honeſtly reprehends his own iudgement formerly deliuered vppon <hi>Plautus,</hi> and <hi>Sidonius Apolinaris;</hi> making (with others) the world a witneſſe of his retractations. So that I may, according to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb,</hi> conclude with <hi>Horace,</hi>
               <q>"Grammatici certant,
<note place="margin">In arte po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etica.</note> et adhuc ſub Iudice lis est.</q> Now, if theſe men may be credited, the Art of <hi>Grammar</hi> is vnperfect: if wee ſhould not credit
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20234:5"/>them, wee are but fooles in my conceit to follow them. For, to learne what is vnperfect, breeds but imperfect knowledge: and I deſpaire of better; in that I am not able to conceiue how thoſe defects which could not in a thouſand eight hundred years paſt (from the time of <hi>Ennius,</hi> till this daie) be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, can at anie time heereafter by the ſame courſe that others haue hitherto followed, bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>V.S. Alb. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gano mag. Aph.</hi> 6.</note> It beeing a follie and againſt all ſenſe to conceiue that thoſe things which were neuer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore brought-to-paſſe, can bee effected by other means then ſuch as no man yet attempted.</p>
            <p>But leauing this vnattempted means to langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges till a fitter opportunitie; let vs,
<note place="margin">Grammarians cenſured.</note> while theſe <hi>Grammarians</hi> are at variance, giue eare to what the Standers-by and men of credit wil ſay of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Craſſus</hi> was of opinion,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic. in. Or. l.</hi> 3</note> that they took a courſe to dull yong wits, &amp; make them ſhameleſs, In learning that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſort was thought ridiculous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plinie</hi> tells vs,
<note place="margin">Com. in Ep.</note> they corrupt the bookes of aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent writers, and make them more obſcure, by their vaine and ouerthwart corrections; and that their curioſities are
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt. nat. l.</hi> 35. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> peruerſe ſubtilties: and that for telling theſe truthes hee alwaies
<note n="*" place="margin">In Prolog. Hiſt. Nat.</note> expected ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from <hi>Grammarians,</hi> in oppoſition of thoſe bookes which he had written <hi>de Grammatica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quintilian</hi> cals their dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce miſchieuous,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious; auouching, that he holds it
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 14</note> fitting, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their other vertues, they ſhould inſert ſome kinde of ignorance. He alſo holds they are vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: And
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epig. l.</hi> 14</note> 
               <hi>Martiall</hi> knew it as well as he; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20234:6"/>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quamuis me Ligulam dicant equiteſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> patreſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dicor ab indoctis Lingula Grammaticis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though I be <hi>Ligula</hi> to th' wiſe and Noble man:</l>
                  <l>Thou call'ſt me <hi>Lingula,</hi> vnlearn'd <hi>Grammarian.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iab.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note> the ſame <hi>Quintilian</hi> tels them plainely, that they may well be able to teach their Scholars to write and ſpeake like <hi>Grammarians,</hi> but they ſhall neuer be able to doe either of them like the Latines:
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> for they are of ſundry conditions; <hi>Aliud eſt Grammaticè, aliud Latinè loqui.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further he ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> that all their Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentaries are full of impediments, &amp; ſuch as are for the moſt part vnknowne vnto themſelues the <hi>Commentators.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this made <hi>Laur: Valla</hi> ſay, there is nothing more arrogant then their eye; or more inſolent in the correction, or rather corruption of Authors.</p>
            <p>Whereupon <hi>Hermolaus Barbarus</hi> reporteth,
<note place="margin">In calce caſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionum ſuarum.</note> that ſome are now adaies growne ſo audacious, as to hold euery thing faultie, and to be corrected, that falls not within the reach of their capacitie: which kind of haſte (ſaith hee) or rather raſhneſſe, is the moſt peſtilent euill that can happen in the latine language.</p>
            <p>And (knowing that <hi>Craſsus</hi> in the time of his Cenſorſhip had by edict put ſuch as theſe to ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) he wiſheth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic. in Ordib.</hi> 3.</note> that (now alſo) there were a law made, whereby ſuch bould and indiſcreet attempts might hereafter wholly be forbidden: Affirming that the vnlearned may ſometimes fall into this error; but the learned more often, and with greater daunger: for, as others are wont to rely much vpon their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20234:6"/>iudgement, ſo are they ſtill able to produce new falſe allurements to perſwade them.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Maſter Tho. Haine</hi> (one of the moſt ſufficient School-maſters about this cittie of London) in
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fol.</hi> 1 <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> a latine Diſcourſe of his, written to the effect of this Appeale,
<note place="margin">Too too dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. <hi>Lud. Viu. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de cauſ. cor. Art.</hi> Say more then they ought, &amp; and yet not all they ſhould.</note> holds ſome <hi>Grammarians</hi> to haue been <hi>nimiùm diligentes;</hi> and that they fall within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of <hi>Quintilian</hi>'s complaint againſt ſuch as <hi>Plura quam par ſit dicunt, non tamen omnia:</hi> And that they haue inriched themſelues, with the ſpoiles of <hi>Lexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons,</hi> &amp; other arts; and adorned their plumes with filched feathers: and that when they haue done what they can, they doe but breake young Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars backes with the burthen of vnneceſſary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts;
<note place="margin">Repetitions of the ſelfe ſame things with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther words.</note> and that ſetting their tender witts vpon the rack they pull and teare them with <hi>Tautologies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other ſome; though (ſaith he) they be ſuccinct, and methodicall in their precepts: yet bring they with them diſaduantage. For no man can run ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to the mark of languages, that is ſhackled and ingiu'd with grammar precepts. And hence it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, that ſuch as onely depend on the rules of <hi>Grammar,</hi> wrote barbarouſly, as appeareth <hi>ex libris Tenebrionumſeu Dunſarum, et ex epiſtolis obſcurorum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum.</hi> And ſuch as attribute much to precepts, and ſomething to authoritie, muſt needes be fearefull, and irreſolute. For, following authoritie, they many times run againſt rules; and obeying rules, they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb authoritie: without whoſe hand and feale, the beſt of rules is but irregulare.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Cominius</hi> concludes, that they teach,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20234:7"/>command children, and ſuch as would learne the tongue, to follow things of a contrary nature. For, firſt they would haue them learn by Grammar, and then they ſend them to reade Authors: which things are contrary.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Deſpauterius</hi> runs with him againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: for he is conſtrained to ſay,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conſtruit Orator propriè,
<note place="margin">In Syntax.</note> quae destruit ipſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grammaticus; quibus eſt fermè contrarius Ordo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What th' Orator builds decently's deſtroy'd</l>
               <l>By the Grammarian, other waies imploy'd.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And in an other place.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si bene diſcutias doctorum ſcripta virorum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Multa ſecus cernes quàm lex vult Grammaticorum.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If thou with care diſcuſſe what wiſe men wrote,</l>
               <l>Thou'l't oft finde other things then <hi>Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mars</hi> note.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Wherevnto <hi>Cicero</hi> alluding,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Or. l.</hi> 1</note> ſaith, I omitt to ſpeak of <hi>Mathematicians, Grammarians,</hi> and <hi>Muſicians;</hi> with whoſe arts, this of Oratorie hath not ſo much as the leaſt coherence.</p>
            <p>Howbeit we are not ignorant (ſaith <hi>Cominius</hi>) that <hi>Grammarians</hi> endeuoring to vphold their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours (either to pleaſe the people,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſt.</hi> 1.5.</note> or (rather) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had no better way to get, or teach by) haue wreſted all the ſentences &amp; authorities of the Ancients, to the approbation of their Art of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar. For whereas <hi>Varro, Quintilian,</hi> and others diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting about Grammar, are inforced to alledge the arguments that may be brought on both ſides; the Grammarians catch thoſe that make for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and produce them as the iudgement, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20234:7"/>eſtabliſhed opinions of the ſame Authors on their behalf: but ſuch arguments as made againſt them, as alſo the concluſions, &amp; abſolute determinations of thoſe Authors in the ſhutting vp of their diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they ouerſlip without remembrance. And therefore, ſaith hee, (though ſomwhat roughly) they haue hitherto deceiued vs, and are themſelues full oft deceiued. Neither doth he exclude our new writers from this cenſure:
<note place="margin">Ep. Reſt.</note> for he houlds that they haue nothing, but what they haue taken from others. And he wrote ſince <hi>Lilies</hi> Grammar was compoſed.</p>
            <p>But, ſaith he,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſt. l.</hi> 1.15</note> let theſe &amp; many other Authors ſpeak their pleaſures, Grammarians wil not be reformed. Trew it is, that finding their collections taxed of being vaine, tedious, diſordered and ſuperfluous; they affect breuitie and better method: but, as they growe ſhorter, ſo are they more inſufficient, and leſs intelligible; euer intricated in the ſelf ſame La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth, commending their reproued precepts, and perſwading all the world to follow them.</p>
            <p>Thus far our Authors haue declared themſelues concerning Grammarians:
<note place="margin">Grammar cenſured.</note> now let vs patiently heare them about their Art.</p>
            <p>It is very likely (ſaith our alledged Author) that thoſe which in ſpeech proceed by Art,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Reſt.</hi>
               </note> rules and reaſon, ought to ſpeake better, then thoſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the people, and ſuch as are vnlearned. So is there a likely hood in muſick, that the diſtances of a third, a fift, a ſixt, and an eight, ſhould by reaſon of theſe numbers, make a concorde, or conſonant
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20234:8"/>harmonie: but (ſaith hee) this dependeth meerely vpon the iudgement of the eare, becauſe God and nature would haue it ſo: And they were not found out by numbers, but by experience; for this obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers therein came afterwards. We may alſo by likelyhood ſay, the Suns riſing is a cauſe of the Cocks crowing; &amp; the ſetting therof of the Owles better ſeeing: But preſumption vpon likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is often a wronger of blameleſſe truth, &amp; an ouerthrowe of greateſt knowledges: and in many things there are ſeeming reaſons at the firſt incoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thought to be irrefragable, which experience at length aſſureth vs to be vaine, and friuolous. And this appeares in Grammar, in that there is a likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode, that all Nounes, and Verbes ſhould followe by <hi>Analogie</hi> the grammaticall Declenſions, and Conjugations:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Priſc. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap. de dat. &amp; abl. plur. ſec. dec.</hi>
               </note> yet looking into Cuſtome, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie wee finde daily ſome irregularities, which we cannot excuſe, or make good, but by new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found exceptions, and inlarging the doctrine of the <hi>Heteroclites.</hi> And all our actions that proceed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are ſooner &amp; better learned by vſe &amp; exerciſe, then by Art,
<note place="margin">Inst. Or.</note> or Precept. For <hi>Quintilian</hi> ſaith, there are many things that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be deliuerd by Art; as, ſucking, eating, drinking, ſtanding, running: to which we may add the actions of our outward ſenſes and the like; which are not onely giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to men, but chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; vnreaſonable creatures. And as in theſe, ſo in ſpeech (which is the ſixt externall ſenſe according to <hi>Raymundus</hi>) we beginne not by Art, but by
<note place="margin">Art. Mag. Plato in Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylo.</note> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and proceed by vſe, cuſtome, authoritie, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20234:8"/>exerciſe, gouern'd by the eare; which is in this kind pleaſed, or diſpleaſed by an inbred, ſecret, &amp; vnpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrable harmony in nature. And let vs be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to know thus much de <hi>facto:</hi> for, of the firſt cauſes we neuer yet had ſolider doctrin, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe likelihoods. Neither will Nature be compeld to dance within our circle; or haue a coat, or a cockſ-comb put vpon her, by her owne Apes; Though I muſt confeſſethat all theſe may be helped by Art, &amp; alſo adorned: But this is not to be vnderſtood in childhood; but in men of iudgement, and of good diſcretion, that are capable of Art, and the reaſons thereof. And that made <hi>Quintilian</hi> ſay, they would doe it better, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted by nature, then by Art;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> yet nature (ſaith hee) hath in it Art.</p>
            <p>But though there be an Art of helping and ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſpeech, yet is it not <hi>Grammar;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Com. lib.</hi> 1.10.</note> except we take it in the firſt ſimplicitie. For, our fore-alledged Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <hi>Cominius</hi> would haue vs knowe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> that <hi>Grammar</hi> hindreth the elegancie of ſpeech: becauſe Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall conſtruction, and precepts, commande that words be otherwiſe placed then antient Authors placed them. And this, ſaith hee, is a great error amongſt vs, that we are now afraide to produce the ſame ſentences, and periods which were vſed by them, in the ſame words that they did, and in their manner of poſition: but by Art of <hi>Grammar</hi> wee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent new words, and put them in an other order, then the beſt Writers placed them; Though <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian</hi> ſay, that if any man diſſolue a clauſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 9.4.</note> ſentence or period that is in it ſelfe ſweet, ful, and wel ſpoken;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20234:9"/>he wil driue away all the force, pleaſure &amp; orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thereof; and altogither foile the compoſition. And he takes his authoritie from <hi>Cicero;</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Or.</note> who, diſſoluing periods of his owne, makes them harſh, &amp; ill-ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: and by correcting the hard, and crabbed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of <hi>Gracchus,</hi> makes them ſweet, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; the better to demonſtrate that, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might haue beene thought but meer imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, it appeareth, that in following Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, we abandon elegancie, and the pleaſure of the eare; and ſpeake and write Grammar-latine, Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latin, Dutch-latine, French-latine: and, in a word, euery nation, by this Art, writes it owne peculiar latine; and not the latine of the <hi>Latins,</hi> nor anie fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine language as it ſhould be. For, in euery tongue there are many things, which if wee ſhould vtter by any other order then as they are vulgarly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, they would not run well, and wee ſhould be thought to ſpeake improperly; as euery man may iudge by the clauſes, ſentences, and eſpecially Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs, of his owne language: which, tranſpoſed, or made-vp with other words than common, would for the moſt part loſe their pleaſing grace, delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſound, and (many times) their ſenſe, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Or. l.</hi> 3</note> Whereupon <hi>Cicero</hi> concludes, that theſe men ſeparate words from ſentences, in the ſame manner that the Soule is ſeparated from the bodie; which is not to be done (ſaith hee) without their manifeſt deſtructions.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1 of the brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vp of youth.</note>
            </p>
            <p>By mine aduice, ſaith * <hi>Aſcham</hi> (who read to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20234:9"/>
               <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi>) a Scholar ſhall not vſe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon order in common ſchooles, for making of Latins: whereby the child commonly learneth firſt an euill choice of words (and right choiſe of words,
<note place="margin">Cic. de clar. Or.</note> ſaith <hi>Caeſar,</hi> is the foundation of eloquence;) then, a wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g placing of words; and laſtly, an euill framing of the ſentence; with a peruerſe iudgement both of words and ſentences. Theſe faults, taking once root in youth, be neuer, or hardly pluckt-away in age.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, there is (ſaith hee) no one thing that hath either dulled the wits, or taken away the wills of children more from learning, then the care they haue to ſatisfy their Maſters in making Latins. For, the Scholar is commonly beaten for the making, when the Maſter were more worthie to be beaten for the mending, or rather marring of the ſame; the Maſter many times being as ignorant as the childe, what to ſay properly, and fitly to the matter And he produceth two Schoolemaſters,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Horman</hi> and <hi>Whittington.</hi>
               </note> which haue ſett foorth in print, either of them, a book of ſuch kinde of Latins, that (if we beleeue him) a childe ſhall learne of the better of them that which an other day (if he be wiſe and com to iudgement) he muſt be faine to vnlearne againe.</p>
            <p>Further: our <hi>Cominius</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſt. l.</hi> 1.9</note> This <hi>Grammar</hi> hinders vs in writing rightly, in reſpect of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſirie of Grammaticall opinions about dipthon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, aſpirations, hiſſings, accents, and infinite other particularities, about which they are euer in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie; as appeareth by <hi>Priſcianus, Tortellius, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilotus, Nicholaus Ferettus, Georgius Valla, Aldus
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20234:10"/>Romanus, Neſtor, Stoa, Friſhlinus,</hi> and a thouſand others; in whom you ſhall finde almoſt nothing but contentions about letters, ſyllables, accents, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of ſyllables, &amp; corrections of Authors, euery man after his owne humour and inuention: ſo that in ſo great a diuerſitie, you are not able to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine how you ſhould proceed either in ſpeaking, or in writing rightly.</p>
            <p>Whereupon he further inferres,
<note place="margin">Ib.</note> that Grammar hinders men from the vnderſtanding of <hi>Poets,</hi> and antient Authours, and makes them more obſcure, and difficult. So that, ſuch as are otherwiſe (for the language ſake) deſirous to reade them, drawe back, and are diſcomfited. And things are brought to that paſſe, that the very name of Latin is hatefull almoſt to euery man; excepting ſuch, as (hunting after gain, and commoditie by ſome ſcience, or profeſſion) are conſtrained to fall vpon the very froth, and dregges therof: and theſe for the moſt part deſpiſe elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and ſcorn ſuch as endeauour to attaine vnto it; in that themſelues are brought-vp vnder the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of Grammar; which neither reſpecteth the names of things, nor the cuſtom of antient Authors, nor the iudgement of the ſenſe of hearing, wherein elegancy hath her maine foundation.</p>
            <p>Beſides:
<note place="margin">Ib.</note> he holdeth it an occaſion of the loſſe of much time, and (conſequently) of many of the beſt and chiefeſt Arts, and knowledges. For, if any man would be exquiſite therein, and ſpeake rightly according to the rules thereof, it is neceſſarie hee ſhould turne ouer the moſt part of Grammaticall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20234:10"/>Commentaries, that he may the better make elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which of them were fitteſt to bee ſollowed; though he confeſſeth,
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> that it would be a perpetuall and an vnprofitable labour, to gather all rules, to examine all places of Authours, and out of all theſe to put all occurrent exceptions vnto rules; in that there is no man but had rather ſpeak after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Cicero, Liuius, Saluſtius, Virgilius, Ouidius, Plautus</hi> &amp; <hi>Terentius,</hi> than vſe the precepts of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians;
<note place="margin">Inſt. Or.</note> 
               <hi>Fabius</hi> houlding it a more excuſable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, to fall in following of theſe great men, than in following of theſe great mens Followers. But (to turne to our election) our Grammarians will queſtionleſſe reject <hi>Priſcianus,</hi> as condemned by <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la;</hi> and <hi>Valla,</hi> as found tripping by <hi>Perottus.</hi> So (to be ſhort) by further inquiſition he will neglect our common Grammar,
<note place="margin">Mr <hi>Gittins.</hi>
               </note> as taxed by him that hath col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected <hi>centum errores Lilij:</hi> And, as wel it, as all other Grammars now in vſe;
<note place="margin">De cauſ. linguae latinae.</note> as branded by <hi>Iulius Caeſar Scaliger,</hi> in aboue ſeuen hundred and fifty noted errours.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing found all the former Grammars faulty; hee cannot warrant the laſt, infallible: yet muſt he be conſtrained to follow it, or make a new one of his owne; which will be liable with the reſt to all taxation. For, by reading antient Authours, he ſhall ſtill diſcouer ſomething that fals not vnder the collections of other Grammarians; and heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon will make an exception to ſome former rule; or make a new rule, and call the former Collecters, block-heads. Thus did our Fathers to our Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20234:11"/>thus will our children deal with vs.</p>
            <p>But ſtay: If, before we can juſtly tax our Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of ignorance, we muſt neceſſarily take pains in reading them; and to read both new and ould Grammarians, were worke enough for a <hi>Methuſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah;</hi> what ſhall we be able to elect or judge of, that haue but a ſpan of life; and in it, before our toppes be ripe, our roots bee rotten? Certainly wee may commence the ſute: but we ſhal neuer liue to hear the Sentence. For, beſides the infinite number of them, the very thought of one onely
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quint. l.</hi> 1.14 <hi>Ariſt. Rhet.</hi> 3. <hi>Zuing. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Didymus,</hi> which wrote but three thouſand and fiue hundred volumes, makes me deſpair of doing well amongſt Grammarians;
<note place="margin">In moriae enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio.</note> Inſomuch that <hi>Eraſmus</hi> concludeth well, that only Grammar is enough to make a man ſpend the circuit of his whole life in tortures.</p>
            <p>And,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſt. l.</hi> 1.9</note> ſaith <hi>Haloinus,</hi> we haue this experience, that many of the Maſter-grammarians (which loſt no time, either in writing of Grammar, or in teaching it) haue been ſo far from perfection in their owne profeſſion, that they were neither able to ſpeak La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine rightly, nor to write it with elegancy.</p>
            <p>Further: wee may note a number of their ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars which haue taken infinite pains til twenty years of age, ſometimes till thirty, and yet are not able to write or ſpeake any thing worth the reading: nor haue they any knowledge in other arts or profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; though they haue ſuffered many ſtripes, and are almoſt deaf with cries and exclamations.</p>
            <p>Half our age,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſſaies, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 25</note> ſaith <hi>Montaigne,</hi> is confumed that way: we are kept foure or fiue years in learning to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20234:11"/>vnderſtand bare words, and to join them into clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; then, as long in proportioning a great bodie extended into foure or fiue parts; and fiue yeares more at leaſt, ere we can ſuccinctly knowe how to mingle, joyn, and interlace them handſomely into a ſubtile faſhion, and into one coherent orb.</p>
            <p>I remember, ſaith <hi>Aſcham,</hi> when I was young,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 2.</note> in the North they went to the Grammar-ſchoole lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children, they came from thence great lubbers; alwaies learning, but little profiting; learning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out book euery thing, vnderſtanding within booke very little: their whole knowledge, by learning without book, was tied onely to their tongue and lips, and neuer aſcended vp to the braines or head; and therefore was ſoon ſpet out again. They were as men alwaies going, but euer out of the way: and why? for, their whole labour (or rather great toile without order) was euen vaine idleneſſe without profit. Indeed, they took great paines about lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; but imployed ſmall labour in learning.</p>
            <p>Now, if Grammar ſhould be the beſt Courſe to languages, and Kings may haue their choiſe of beſt Courſes; I wonder what choiſe of Grammars was made by <hi>Mithridates.</hi> And that, that makes mee wonder more: we, that haue no buſineſſe but a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, ſpend all our life, and are not perfect in one; and hee, that had a Kingdomes affairs to look vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, had two and twenty compleat languages.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Val. Max. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 7</note>
            </p>
            <p>I wonder alſo how the <hi>Romans</hi> came all to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in <hi>Oratory, Husbandry, Astrologie, Geometry, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetick, Muſick,</hi> and many other ſciences, before
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20234:12"/>they were admitted to martiall diſcipline, or other imployment: as by <hi>Livius, Valerius, Plutarch, Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius, Frontinus, Vegetius,</hi> and many others, is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Aſſuredly, they knew no Grammar: or, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, they did neglect it.</p>
            <p>And no maruell: for, <hi>Alexander, Amigonus, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles, Themiſtocles, Epaminondas, Hanibal, Scipio,</hi> and a thouſand others, were inſtructed by <hi>Ariſtotle, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſthenes, Leonides, Perſeus, Phenix, Phreareus, Lyſias, Socilaus, Terentius,</hi> and the like. And all theſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Potentates were knowne learned, almoſt in all ſciences, through the aſſiſtance of theſe and other Maſters. Of whom, ſome were Oratours; ſome, Poets; ſome, Philoſophers, and of other profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but, none of them were found to bee Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians.</p>
            <p>Yet now adaies,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 1.9.</note> ſaith <hi>Cominius,</hi> they are ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, that if a man would pen an eloquent Oration after the manner of the Antients, were it neuer ſo pleaſing and ſufficient; if hee obſerue not, euerie where, the Grammar-rules, hee dares not vtter it, for fear of being thought to ſpeak incongruouſly. And of this I was lately my ſelf a witnes; where a Gentleman, making a Verſe to his owne purpoſe, and imitating in all points <hi>Martiall,</hi> was by one, that thought himſelfe a great Proficient, reprehended for falſe Latine: But, the Gentleman producing his Authour, the <hi>Critick</hi> was half diſparaged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haloinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1. <hi>Reſt.</hi>
               </note> coming yet a little neerer the quick, tels vs (and it ſtands with reaſon) that no Grammar can bee made perfect, vnleſſe it were as often renewed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20234:12"/>as new words are coined, or ould ones newly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Neither can it, ſaith he, be perfect, vnleſſe it teach vs the Dialects of Nations, or the diuerſities of language and pronounciation in ſundry Regions, Prouinces, and diſtant places; with the changes and alterations in the maner of ſpeaking, as well in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine as in other languages.</p>
            <p>And our experience giues vs to vnderſtand, that not onely thoſe of <hi>Flanders, Brabant, Holland, Zeland,</hi> and others in the lower-<hi>Germanie;</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>var, Aragon, Catalonia, Galicia</hi> and <hi>Portugall,</hi> in <hi>Spain;</hi> and our owne Eaſtern, Weſtern, Northerne, Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern, and middle parts of <hi>England,</hi> doe much vary one and the ſelf-ſame language: but euery twenty-miles-diſtance from any place, yeelds a manifeſt differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the tongues of all, or any of theſe parts or Prouinces; as alſo euery twenty yeares alters e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of the ſaid differences. Inſomuch that few of vs, if we conſider the antient Records and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours of our Nation, can beleeue, that a Grammar made in the time of <hi>Chaucer, Robert</hi> of <hi>Gloſter,</hi> or of <hi>Aelſrick,</hi> can be vſefull now in ours; though doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe theſe men wrote in the choiſeſt Dialect the time afforded. And, certainely, all other Dialects are and will be changed in the ſame proportion.</p>
            <p>Now, if Grammars bee compoſed according to the purity of ſpeech eſpecially; and the puritie of ſpeech in any nation is thought to be at the height, at that very inſtant that the Grammar was or is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; and that euery time and place, according to the alteration &amp; inconſtancy of that inſtant, is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20234:13"/>altered and inconſtant: I cannot ſee how anie Grammars of any languages, that are not daily (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe alterations) altered, can be of any certainty or perfection; in that, as a Grammar is made to be vniuerſall, ſo ſhould it, according to the Authours intention, be perpetuall: which, for the reaſons alledged, is in both impoſſible.</p>
            <p>For,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1.2</note> ſaith my Author, if words be changed, it is neceſſary that Conjugations, Declenſions, Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, Tenſes, Moods, and all other Grammaticall obſeruations (in what tongue ſoeuer) be alſo chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: which ſince it is impoſſible, the perfection al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is impoſſible.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Ludovicus Vives</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Be corr. art. l.</hi> 2</note> that after Grammar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms or precepts were inuented out of a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable correſpondencie of Art; ſome haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to draw the immeaſurable ſtream of <hi>vſe</hi> through them, as through fitting trenches or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels: whereas <hi>Grammar,</hi> with <hi>Logick</hi> and <hi>Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> were obſerued and deriued from <hi>vſe;</hi> and not vſe, from them. Therefore they haue not onely weakned and broken ſpeech, by reducing it vnto the poore and penurious preſcript of Grammar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rules; but haue alſo corrupted it with many errors, in that they haue ſpoken otherwiſe than they ought to doo: well, in reſpect of rules; but ill, in reſpect of cuſtome, which is the <hi>Lady and Miſtreſſe</hi> of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. You may ſee full many moſt exact Maſters of th' Art in this manner pollute their ſpeech with foule enormities, whil'ſt they follow Art, which is not capable of vſe; becauſe vſe is various or change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20234:13"/>neither doth it follow Grammar or Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie; and therefore all things could not bee rightly gathered.</p>
            <p>This beeing ſufficiently knowne vnto the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents; though this Art, as <hi>suetonius</hi> reporteth,
<note place="margin">de claris Gram.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan at the firſt to draw many (as is vſuall) through the nouelty thereof, and by a likelyhood of reaſon, and vain hopes that depended thereon: yet <hi>Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Ep. Reſt.</note> ſubſcribing to the fore-alledged opinion of <hi>Martial,</hi> ſaith, If any man read with diligence, and examine antient Authors, hee ſhall finde, that the Roman Nobility, the men of authority, the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and the learnedeſt Citizens, neuer followed that Art, or euer approued it: neither was it at any time praiſed or receiued by Poets, Orators, Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, or any other of perfection: but, true it is, ſaith he, they diſcommended, ſcorned and rejected, as well Grammar, as Grammarians.</p>
            <p>Neither did <hi>Quintilian</hi> think,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10</note> that this Art was ſent from heauen when men were firſt formed, to giue lawes of ſpeaking; but that it was found out after they ſpake, and had taken notice how euerie thing did ſound in vtterance: for many, ſaith <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius,</hi> whoſe labours for the moſt part periſhed in the combuſtion of the Gothes, as <hi>Actius, Pacuvius, Plautus, Navius, Livius, Andronicus, Laberius, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretius,</hi> and manie others, wrote Latine before this Art of Grammar was inuented; and are cited by <hi>Nonius Marcellus, Aulus Gellius, Macrobius, Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cianus,</hi> and other Writers. And no man doubteth, but the Inuenters of Grammar had the language
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20234:14"/>before they had the Art; and muſt therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that it may be learned without Art.</p>
            <p>And the ſame <hi>Quintilian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Inſt.</hi>
               </note> conſidering how much this Art had (by the beſt ſort of people) been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, ingenuouſly confeſſeth, that hee, in what he wrote of Grammar, did not vndertake to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an Art thereof: but, it comming in the way of his diſcourſe, he would not omit to ſpeak of it, leſt exceptions might bee taken, that hee ſhould ſlight and vnder-value it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cicero,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Or. l.</hi> 1.</note> alluding heerunto, ſaith, I vnderſtand the power and force of all precepts to be thus; not that <hi>Orators</hi> had the name of being eloquent by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; but that ſome obſerued and did thoſe things, which of their owne accord had made men eloquent: ſo that eloquence is not bred of Art; but Art, of eloquence. Yet I reject it not, ſaith he: for, though it bee not ſo neceſſary to teach a man to ſpeak well, yet the knowledge thereof is not illibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. And in the ſame maner may we ſay, that ſpeech was not bred of Grammar; but it, of ſpeech: and, if the precepts of <hi>Orators</hi> are not ſo neceſſary in well-ſpeaking, what ſhall we gather of the precepts of Grammarians?</p>
            <p>Let vs leaue them to thoſe whoſe profeſſion they are,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſſaies,</hi> 1.25.</note> ſaith <hi>Montaigne;</hi> and let vs that ſeeke, not to frame a Grammarian, but a compleat Gentleman, giue them leaue to miſ-ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their time in precepts: wee haue elſe-where to doo, and ſomewhat elſe of more importance. There are that knowe neither Ablative, Conjunctive, Subſtantive, nor Grammar;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20234:14"/>no more doth their Lackey, nor any Oyſter-wife about the ſtreets: and yet (if you haue a minde thereto) they will entertain you your fill, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture ſtumble as little and as ſeldome againſt the rules of their Tongue, as the beſt Maſter of arts in <hi>France.</hi> And, ſaith he,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſſaies, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> I hate ſuch as can brag of their rules of Grammar, and can neither write nor ſpeak a language; and ſo doo others: nay, ſaith he, I finde the choiſeſt men were they that moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned them.</p>
            <p>Thus it appeares, ſaith <hi>Cominius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>l a. c.</hi> 10. <hi>Reſt.</hi>
               </note> that this Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, which giues rules and lawes of ſpeaking, that now euery where is taught, is a deceitfull, vain and vnprofitable Art; drawing men on, onely by like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihoods. And it may wel be ſaid, to be a Labyrinth: for, ſuch as are brought vp, and are Proficients in it, can finde no way to winde them out againe. Some of them perceiue they are intangled, and intimate as much to all men in their works, though but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely: yet for gains ſake they commend it, teach it, and profeſſe it. Wherefore, ſaith hee,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 15.</note> I cannot but grieue and lament, that in ſo cloudy and ſo falſe an Art, ſo many men, and of ſo exquiſite an vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſhould thus long be deceiued &amp; ſtupefied. And that which makes me grieue the more, is, that by it all antient elegancy, the Art of <hi>Oratorie, Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick,</hi> and many other Arts and knowledges, haue periſhed, been ſtifled, and abandoned.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Scaliger</hi> did often wonder at the preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſtubbornneſſe of ſuch as were vpholders of other mens errours:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De cauſ. linguae latinae. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 67</note> whereas if they which had
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20234:15"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted them were now aliue again, they would recant them. Neither is it ſo great an offence to erre: for, it is the beginning of wiſdome; if not to him that was deceiued; yet to others, that they may not deceiue. But to foſter errors, is either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of madnes and folly; or like the choiſe of thoſe, who being once or twice foiled, had rather be ſtain then reconciled.</p>
            <p>I cannot thinke,
<note place="margin">VSE AP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PROVED</note> theſe antient Authours would in this manner ſlight either Grammar or Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians; had they thought the Tongues of Nations might haue been ſufficiently learn'd by their gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall rules or precepts: for, none made more account of ſpeech then they did; or were more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in adorning it; or more deſir'd to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and poſterity, Oratours and eloquent: but they knew full well, that there were other courſes to come ſooner, and with greater eaſe in all perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vnto languages: whereof though ſomething haue been ſaid already; yet, becauſe wee haue had the judgements of graue men to diſſwade from Art and precepts, let vs alſo vſe them to direct vs to that way of greater benefit.</p>
            <p>If we ask <hi>Quintilian</hi> what this way is;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſt. Or. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10</note> he will tell vs plainely, that Cuſtome is the beſt approoued School-miſtreſs for languages; and that all the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines were taught by vſe and cuſtome, from the mouthes of nurſes and other women which had the keeping of them, from their cradle; and not by Grammar or Grammarians, as was erroneouſly thought by <hi>Leonardus Aretinus,</hi> and his Followers.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20234:15"/>And he boldly affirmeth, that ſpeech depends not on reaſon, but example: neither will he hear of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other law therein, but obſeruation; or that the Art it ſelf had any ground or foundation, but in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome.</p>
            <p>Experience alſo confirms, that if wee ſpeak not according to cuſtom, few or none will giue vs hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: and, amongſt thoſe that will, the moſt part of them will deride vs, becauſe they cannot vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand our meaning. Whereupon,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.11</note> the Apoſtle ſaith, If I know not the meaning of the voice, I ſhall be vnto him that ſpeaketh a <hi>Barbarian;</hi> and hee that ſpeaketh ſhall be a <hi>Barbarian</hi> vnto me.</p>
            <p>Yet was this cuſtome limited by the <hi>iudgement of hearing:</hi> and therefore <hi>Cominius</hi> ſaith, Cuſtom,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11</note> concurring with the pleaſure of hearing, is the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt rule and foundation of the latine language.</p>
            <p>By Cuſtome, antient Authours vnderſtand the common form of ſpeaking vſed by the people; and eſpecially, as <hi>Quintilian</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſt. Or. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 12</note> by conſent of that part of them that are learned. But, ſaith <hi>Cominius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11</note> theſe learned muſt be ſuch as are leaſt tainted with grammaticall inſtructions, or corrupted with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern cuſtome: for, ſaith hee, <hi>Quintilian</hi> vnderſtood not the conſent of Grammarians; but of men, that by much knowledge and experience came by lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and vnderſtanding; as being exerciſed by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent cuſtome of ſpeaking, both in priuate and in publique places; and of ſuch as reſorted daily to Princes Palaces; as, <hi>Cicero, Caeſar, Livius, Saluſtius,</hi> and the like, who as well in warre as peace were
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20234:16"/>Courtiers; and joyned to their owne learning much other ſtudie and diligence in reading, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of all other matters that might inrich their Tongue in ſpeaking.</p>
            <p>And if any man read <hi>Cicero</hi>'s works <hi>de perfecto O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratore,</hi> and <hi>de claris Oratoribus,</hi> he ſhall alſo finde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſentences of the judgement, pleaſure, meaſure, and ſweetnes of the ear: whereunto he concludes, all Tongues and euery ſpeech of man is tied, and muſt be ſubject; as well in proſe, as in verſe or poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ord.</hi> 3</note> for heerunto, ſaith hee, and not vnto Art, the Tongue and cuſtom of the antient Latines was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
            <p>In a verſe, we look, ſaith hee, as well to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and middle, as the end thereof; and wee ſpoil all, if wee faile in any part: but in proſe, few mark the beginnings, but moſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mark the ending Cadences; which becauſe they appear and are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of, they are to be varied, leſt they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by the judicious, and through ſatiety growe odious.</p>
            <p>But, ſaith he, leſt any man ſhould admire, how the very weakeſt ſort of thoſe that are vnlearned ſhould take notice of theſe ſounds &amp; endings, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the wiſeſt and moſt vnderſtanding hearers doe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh; let him knowe, that nature hath, as well in euery other thing as in this, a kind of ſtroke more then ordinary. For, euery man by a ſecret feeling diſcerneth thoſe things without Art, which are right or wrong in Art and reaſon; which, ſince they doe in pictures, ſtatua's, and in other worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20234:16"/>to whoſe vnderſtanding their inſtrument ſo well ſerues them not; they ſhew, they are much better able to judge of words, of numbers, and of voices. For, theſe are things that run with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſenſe: neither would Nature haue any man to be wholly without the knowledge of them. For, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing art is produced out of nature; except ſhe moue nature and delight her, ſhee ſeemeth not indeed to haue done any thing. For, there is nothing that hath ſo neer an alliance with our ſoules, as numbers and voices: for, by them wee are provoked, infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, appeaſed, and growe timorous, &amp; are brought to mirth and melancholie.</p>
            <p>But, ſaith our Authour, as in verſe the Vulgar finde what is amiſſe: ſo in our proſe, if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny haulting, they perceiue it. And they pardon not the Poet, though they wink at vs: yet inwardly they knowe, that what we alſo ſaid was neither apt nor perfect. Whereby, <hi>Cicero</hi> giues vs to vnderſtand, that all ſpeech, whether proſe or verſe, dependeth vpon the judgement of our hearing; and that it muſt by Orators, as well as Poets, be regarded, that euery man in hearing may be pleaſed.</p>
            <p>And this is not only commanded by our antient Authours, but acknowledged and preſcribed by Grammarians: for, <hi>Diomedes</hi> is by <hi>Deſpauterius</hi> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſaying thus; Wee muſt alwaies bee carefull of
<note place="margin">Good ſound, or pleaſant vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance of words. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>aut.</hi> 13. <hi>Noct. Attic. c.</hi> 19</note> 
               <hi>Euphonia:</hi> for, <hi>Euphonia</hi> in words is ſometimes of more worth in ſpeech, then is Analogie or Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar-precepts.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> (or, as late <hi>Criticks</hi> call him,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20234:17"/>
               <hi>Agellius</hi>) ſaith, Amongſt the eleganteſt Writers, there was more account made of the ſweet ſound of words and voices, called <hi>Euphonia</hi> by the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; than of the rule or diſcipline which was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued by the Grammarians.</p>
            <p>But let <hi>Gellius, Macrobius,</hi> or others, ſay what they pleaſe; they almoſt all proceed by Art, and not by hearing,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſt.</hi> 1.12</note> ſaith <hi>Cominius.</hi> And whatſoeuer they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge in this kinde, they ſtill return to Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> 13</note> and leaue the vſe and cuſtome of ſpeech, that hath been ſo much celebrated by our Anceſtours.</p>
            <p>Had <hi>Cominius</hi> read the Preface to our Engliſh Grammar, he would doubtleſſe haue acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that our better ſort of School-maſters haue an honeſt deſire to follow the beſt, eaſieſt, and moſt ready way to languages: for, ſaith hee that wrote that Preface, It is not amiſſe if one, ſeeing by triall an eaſier and readier way than the common ſort of Teachers doo, would ſay what he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and for the commodity allowed; that other, not knowing the ſame, might by experience proue the like, and then by proof reaſonable judge the like: not heerby excluding the better way when it is found; but in the meane ſeaſon forbidding the worſe. Yet I muſt needs with <hi>Cominius</hi> confeſſe, They ſtill reflect vpon ſome Grammar: for, all this ſpeech hath relation to our common Grammar; and that, becauſe they know not how to bring that way of cuſtome into practice.</p>
            <p>For, though ſome will grant, that in the vulgar languages of Nations, Vſe and Cuſtome may doo
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20234:17"/>much: yet for ſuch Tongues as haue their maine foundation in the works of antient Writers, and are now in vſe onely amongſt Scholars, they cannot think of any courſe, but onely Grammar.</p>
            <p>And yet I make no doubt, but theſe men wil gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that the beſt and moſt imitable part of Cuſtome, whether in languages extinct or flouriſhing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in Authors; and that (as well in Greek &amp; La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, as any other vſuall Tongues) there is no want of worthy Authors. Now, we that deſire not to follow the droſſe of Cuſtom, but the purity; what ſhould keep vs from learning languages alſo by written Vſe and Cuſtome? which is common, not alone to thoſe that are in daily vſe; but alſo ſuch as are extinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>They 'l ſay, In ſuch as are extinct we cannot hear or imitate the cuſtome of their natiue Tone, their accent and deliuery.</p>
            <p>'Tis true: but, finding none aliue that may bee made our lawful Iudges heerin, let euery man hold that to bee the beſt that's judged beſt by his owne Nation.</p>
            <p>They 'l tell me, that the ſame in euery School is at this Preſent put in practice.</p>
            <p>I acknowledge, it is done as well as their Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar-bounds will ſuffer it: but, this is but <hi>Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticè.</hi> I would haue it, as the Authours themſelues would haue it, to bee done <hi>Latinè,</hi> and without the Grammar.</p>
            <p>But, this reducement of Cuſtome to practice,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiections. </seg>2</label> hath been thought firſt impoſſible; and then, ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20234:18"/>impoſſible, becauſe it neither is nor hath been found out, nor heard of; ridiculous, in that, beeing to be done without the rules of Grammar, it would bee done without all reaſon, and ſuch as learn ſhould learn like Parrats.</p>
            <p>Th' objection of impoſſibility makes mee ſmile,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>1</label> that knowe and finde it feſible: and that inference [it cannot] drawn and wreſted from [it is, or hath not] breeds but a deceitfull argument.</p>
            <p>About the being ridiculous,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>2</label> becauſe thought to be without reaſon; is but a ridiculous reaſon: for, though I knowe the world to bee poſſeſt, that hee onely giues a reaſon that giues a Grammar-rule; yet, if I ſhould ask them what were the reaſon of that rule, it were impoſſible that they ſhould giue me any other reaſon then this written Cuſtome or Authority. Wherefore, theirs and ours is one and the ſame reaſon: different in nothing, but that they relie on the Dependent; wee, on the Principall: which I hould the better and the neerer reaſon, and the reaſon of their reaſon. And yet, if I be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, there is a greater difference: for, Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, in th' expoſition of Authours, tell their ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, that this or that conſtruction is by reaſon of this or that rule; but truth it ſelf will tell vs other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: for, out of thoſe Authours, this or that was made a rule, by reaſon of this or that conſtruction. And, in my poore opinion, it is a more allowable anſwer to ſay, <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid ſo; than to ſay, <hi>Priſcianus</hi> ſaies that <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid ſo.</p>
            <p>Some, that are thus far conuinced and brought
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20234:18"/>forward, fall vpon this block of opinion, that they are bound (as, of this, or that Vniuerſity) to defend Grammar: which is like that old and rotten poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Wee are bound rather to erre with the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, than to follow truth with two or three.</p>
            <p>But theſe are ſuch as doe not perceiue, that in <hi>Grammatica</hi> there is a thing required beſides the name and ſhadow thereof. The thing is that, that they are tied vnto; which is, the Art of writing &amp; of ſpeaking rightly (which, though it may bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of Grammar in the firſt ſimplicity; yet let vs now take it as they doe): this thing if it be not to be found in ordinary Grammars, they are bound to ſeek it elſewhere; and where they really do find it, there to honour and obſerue it; whether vnder name or title of <hi>Grammatica, Logonomia,</hi> or what elſe ſoeuer, ſo the thing be there: for, though it ſhould haue the propereſt name in opinion that might be; if the thing bee abſent, all's but deceit and vanity. And, for mine owne part, I haue as long ſuckt the milk of Vniuerſities, and acknowledge as much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and obedience vnto them, as many others; and therfore haue ſome reaſon to knowe their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue to be ſuch, that, what we receiue, they had rather ſhould turne to holeſome and effectuall nouriſhment, than a ſeeming and diſeaſing fulneſs. But, let deeds diſpute the reſt, and let vs returne to Cuſtome: in which, I had rather ſatisfie the world with other mens authority, than mine owne opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And to this purpoſe <hi>Cominius</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſt.</hi> 1.13.</note> If wee would
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20234:19"/>followe the example of auntient Authors, <hi>Orators, Hiſtorians,</hi> and <hi>Poets,</hi> either in <hi>Latine,</hi> or in <hi>Greeke;</hi> and ſhould be exerciſed in their cuſtome of ſpeaking, which wee finde within their writings;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> 1.11.</note> there is no doubt but wee may arriue vnto their very height of elegancy.</p>
            <p>But, there are fower eſpeciall reaſons, alledged by mine Author, why fewe, or none perceiue the cuſtome of the Auntients.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they put whatſoeuer they would ſpeake, word for word, into an other language, in the ſame order wherin they ſpeake it in their owne. Now, though this may in ſome fall out well; yet there are manie ſpeaches, ſentences, prouerbs, ſayings and authorities, of two wordes onely, or of moe; which, tranſlated into three or foure languages, are to be ſet downe in euery one after a diuerſe order, and other wordes are to bee receiued. For, euery tongue hath proper and peculiar words, which are neither agreeable to other tongues, or lyable to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation; by which the eleganter ſayings, the grauer ſentences, and the more vſuall prouerbs are eſpecially co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſed. Wherfore they are deceyued, which ſpeake according to the order of other lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages: which is knowne to be much vſed, &amp; moſt amongſt the more vnlearned.</p>
            <p>Secondly: though ſuch as follow Grammar, and are a middle ſort of Scholars, do not alwayes tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flate verbally; yet they ſpeak not by the order, and cuſtome of the Auntients; but, place their words after a grammaticall order, and conſtruction; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20234:19"/>obeying the rules, and precepts of Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, than the cuſtome of the Auntients, and the iudgement of hearing: which is contrarie to the precepts of <hi>Cicero.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly: though the learned ſort, and ſuch as would be called Poets, and Orators, tranſlate not alwayes word for word; nor doe euery where ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a grammaticall conſtruction: yet they come not neere the Latine elegancie; as hauing beene brought vp from their child-hood by th' Art of Grammar, and Analogy. They take a pride to frame new words, without regard vnto the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the eare: which though they bee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes placed according to the order of the Aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, yet are they harſh, and without elegancie; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not moderated, and meaſured by th' eare, as their Aunceſtors would haue them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly: the greater part of men, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the learneder ſort, are aſhamed forſooth, to ſpeak in the ſame words, and in the ſame order pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that the Auntients ſpake them; leſt it might be caſt in their teeth, that they knew not how to ſpeak of themſelues, without vſing the wayes, and words of others.</p>
            <p>From theſe fore-alledged reaſons, there ariſe (ſaith hee) innumerable <hi>Soloeciſm's,</hi> and <hi>Barbariſms,</hi> not onely in the <hi>Latine,</hi> but all other languages: of which, ſaith he, Grammarians dream many things; but I dare ſay, that fewe of them know what either a <hi>Soloeciſm,</hi> or a <hi>Barbariſm</hi> meaneth; becauſe they make all to haue relation to their Grammar. And I
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20234:20"/>ſo much the rather beleeue him, in that Our <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſius</hi> Dictionary tranſlates the word <hi>Soloeciſmus, Incongruitie;</hi> euen to th' eleuenth Edition. And, ſaith he, By how much the more they endeauour to flee theſe <hi>Solaeciſms,</hi> ſo much the more and oftner by their rules and precepts doo they fall into them. For,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſt. Or. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9</note> 
               <hi>Quintilian</hi> ſaith, <hi>Soloeciſmus non eſt in ſenſu, ſed in complexu;</hi> is not in the ſenſe, but in the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the words, or foulding of them one with another:
<note place="margin">Ib.</note> which in * another place he makes more manifeſt; ſaying, A <hi>Soloeciſme</hi> is an inconuenient placing of laſt and firſt together in a ſpeech of one ſentence; meaning, by <hi>inconvenient,</hi> that which is not in vſe among the antient Writers. For, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is in vſe, is neither inconuenient, nor a <hi>Soloe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, let Grammarians conſider the deceit of their Art: for, I will proue, ſaith hee, that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce many <hi>Soloeciſmus</hi> and <hi>Barbariſms</hi> in the latine language; and I will admit of no other teſtimonies heerin, then ſuch as are of their owne profeſſion. For <hi>Servius,</hi> which is called the Prince of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians, writeth, that the Art of Grammar com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth many precepts to be followed, againſt cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and the vſe of antient Authours. So ſaith <hi>Nonius Marcellus</hi> alſo: which being true, it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily followes, that they command and teach men many <hi>Soloeciſms.</hi> And that made <hi>Servius</hi> ſay, The authority of th' Antients confoundeth Art; and <hi>Quintilian,</hi> that there are ſome things that cannot be deliuered by Art:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> for, if the caſe wee beganne
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20234:20"/>withall be harſh, it is to be changed: wherein hee ſheweth, that all grammaticall proceedings ſhould be altered, if th' ear be not well pleaſed. And that made <hi>Cicero</hi> ſay,
<note place="margin">In Or.</note> Wee ought rather to offend in Art, than in the ſweetnes of the eare. Which, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Marcellus</hi> ratifieth; ſhewing, that caſes, genders, tenſes, conjugations, declenſions, and all other grammaticall precepts, are often changed by anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Authours, againſt the rules and precepts of Grammarians; as well in proſe, by <hi>Cicero, Livius,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>l.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Reſt.</hi>
                  </note> Saluſtius,</hi> and the like; as in verſe, by <hi>Catullus, Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Ovidius, Lucanus,</hi> and other of the beſt &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt Poets. And thus they wound themſelues, ſaith he, with their owne weapons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſcham,</hi> citing the words of <hi>Salustius,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>f.</hi> 66.</note> Multis ſibi quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> imperium petentibus,</hi> ſaith; I beleeue, the beſt Grammarian in <hi>England</hi> can ſcarſe giue a good rule, why <hi>quiſque,</hi> the nominatiue caſe without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Verb, is ſo thruſt vp amongſt ſo many oblique caſes. I muſt confeſſe, he condemns him for it: but, by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Aſchams</hi> leaue, if I could not better out of better Authors expreſſe my ſelf, I had rather truſt <hi>Saluſt</hi> in the Latine, than M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Aſcham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It followes therefore, that they labour in vaine, that hope to write or ſpeak eloquent Latine, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther languages; and would make their way there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by learning or following Grammar. For (as it is ſaid) if the laſt did juſtly and deſeruedly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the former, then could not the former teach vs to write or ſpeak rightly: but, if the laſt did vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſeruedly reprehend the reſt, it is impoſſible that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20234:21"/>hee ſhould teach vs. Now, if nor firſt nor laſt can teach vs, then may we juſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude with our alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Authors, that of Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marians there's none ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teach vs.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſt. l.</hi> 1.15.</note> Wherefore, <hi>Cominius</hi> aboue an hundred years ſince ſaid, It was neceſſary that we ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect others: but, if any man would further knowe why or to what end we ſhould expect them, hee is lately moſt learnedly anſwered;
<note place="margin">Vic. S. Alb. Org. mag. vel Reſt. Mag.</note> 
               <hi>Vt res de integro ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetur melioribus praeſidijs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thoſe that are expected to new-mould the way to languages, muſt draw their courſe by Vſe and Cuſtome, till <hi>Babel</hi> be reformed by <hi>Zorobabel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1.15. <hi>R.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Cominius,</hi> if wee exerciſe our ſelues in Vſe and Cuſtome, we ſhall ſooner, eaſier, and more ſecurely attain vnto the elegancy of the latine lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; than by art, or all the rules thereof: for, by exerciſe of reading, writing, and ſpeaking after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Cuſtome, wee ſhall conceiue three things which are of greateſt moment in any languages: firſt, the true and certain declining and conjugating of words, and all things belonging to Grammar, will without labour, and whether wee will or no, thruſt themſelues vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee ſhall taſte of the manner of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vſed by the Antients, together with the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, grace, pleaſure, and delightfulneſſe of the Latine.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we ſhall get the judgement of the eare, and retaine the ſame for euer: which, Grammar cannot helpe vs to; in that it is imperfect, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guileth vs.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:20234:21"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Linacer, Camden,</hi> and ſome others, haue made them ſtiles of ſome perfection: yet they'l tell you in your eare, that they haue gotten it rather by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and a memory or taſte of the cuſtome of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, after reading, and practice vpon that taſte; than by Art, rule or precept. For, if it be well exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, we ſhall finde few ſcholars arriued to a lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable ſtile of writing, but haue forgot the moſt part of their Grammar-precepts. And indeed, the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they leaue them, and fall to reading, and after it to writing; the ſooner doo they come to their perfection.</p>
            <p>Wee finde, that ſuch as are brought vp by Vſe, and exerciſe, in any other ſciences, are for the moſt part in ſhort time great Proficients: nay, if we look into the ordinary Tongues of Nations, there are none ſo harſh or difficult, either in ſpeaking or in writing, wherein a boy that ſhall be exerciſed, will not within the compaſs of two or three years with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Art, but meerly by vſe, example, obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and eare, growe very perfect. Which, our Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellers might with my ſelf obſerue in the lower &amp; higher <hi>Germany, Bohemia, Italie, Spain, France,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries, in children of our owne and other Nations: As alſo that among the <hi>Polonians,</hi> and in many other regio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, there are euery where ſeruants, boyes and wenches, found to ſpeak both good and congruous Latine; and that without all Art, but ear and exerciſe.</p>
            <p>Which, <hi>Montaign</hi> vereſies in his own perſon;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſſaies, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 25</note> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vs this following Hiſtory. I muſt needs, ſaith
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20234:22"/>he acknowledge that the <hi>Greek</hi> &amp; <hi>Latin</hi> tongues are great ornaments in a Gentleman; but, they are pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed at an ouer-high rate. Vſe it, who liſt: I will tell you how they may bee gotten better cheape, &amp; much ſooner than is ordinaryly vſed; which was tried in myne owne education.</p>
            <p>My late father (hauing, by all poſſible means &amp; induſtrie, ſought amongſt the wiſeſt and men of beſt vnderſtanding, to finde a moſt exquiſite and readie way of teaching) being aduiſed of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences then in vſe, was giuen to vnderſtand that the lingring while, and beſt part of our youth that wee imploy in learning the tongues (which coſt the <hi>Greekes,</hi> and <hi>Latines</hi> nothing) is the onely cauſe that wee can neuer attaine to their abſolute perfection of skill, and knowledge. I doe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that, to be the onely cauſe. But, ſo it is, that the expedient my father found out was this, that being yet at nurſe, and before the firſt looſing of my tongue, I was deliuered to a Germane (who dyed, ſince, a moſt excellent Phyſicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <hi>Fraunce</hi>) hee being altogether ignorant of the French tongue, but exquiſitely readie and skil-full in the Latine. This man, whome my father had ſent for of purpoſe, and to whome he gaue very great enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement, had me continually in his armes, &amp; was myne onely Ouerſeer. There were alſo ioyned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him two of his countrie-men, but not ſo learned, whoſe charge was to attend, and now and then to play with me; and all theſe togither did neuer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine me with other than the Latine tongue. As
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20234:22"/>for others of his howſehould, it was an inviolable rule, that neither himſelfe, nor my mother, nor man nor maide-ſeruaunt were ſuffered to ſpeake one word in my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie; except ſuch Latine-wordes, as euery one had learned to chatt and prattle with me. It were ſtrange to tell, how euery one in the howſe profited therein. My father and my mother learned ſo much Latine, that for a need they could vnderſtand it, when they heard it ſpoken: ſo did all the howſhold ſeruants; namely, ſuch as were nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and moſt about mee. To bee ſhort: wee were all ſo Latinized, that the townes round about vs had their ſhare of it; In ſo much, as euen at this daie, many Latine names both of workmen, and their tooles, are yet in vſe amongſt them. And as for my ſelfe, I was about ſix yeares oulde, and could vnderſtand no more French, or Perigordine, then Arabick; &amp; that without Art, without books, rules, or Grammar, without whipping, or whyning, I had gotten as pure a Latine tongue as my Maſter could ſpeake; the rather becauſe I could neither mingle or confound the ſame, with other tongues. If for an eſſaye they would giue mee a Theame; whereas the faſhion in Colledges is to giue it in French, I had it in bad Latine, to reduce the ſame into good. And <hi>Nicholas Grucchi,</hi> who hath written <hi>de comitijs Romanorum; William Guerenti,</hi> who hath commented Ariſtotle; <hi>George Buchanan,</hi> that famous Scottiſh <hi>Poet;</hi> and <hi>Mark Authony Muret,</hi> whom (whileſt he liued) both <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and <hi>Ralie</hi> to this daie acknowledge, to haue beene the beſt Orator;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20234:23"/>all theſe haue beene my familiar Tutors, and haue often told me, that in mine infancy I had the Latin Tongue ſo ready and ſo perfect, that themſelues feared to take me in hand. And <hi>Buchanan</hi> (whom afterwards I ſaw attending on the Marſhall of <hi>Briſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack</hi>) tould me, he was about to write a Treatiſe of the inſtitution of children, and that hee took the modell and patern thereof from mine.</p>
            <p>And this Form of teaching and learning of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages was of that authority with <hi>Ludovicus Vives,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De corr. Art. l.</hi> 2</note> that he confeſſeth, he had rather be thus imployed for one year, than to beſtowe ten yeers to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vnder the beſt and moſt reputed Schoole-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
            <p>The practice alſo of written Vſe and Cuſtome, which I ſhewed to a moſt graue, wiſe, and powerfull Noble-man of this Kingdome, did ſo content him, that he ſpared not to tell me, hee had rather giue ten pounds a month to haue his childe haue this inſtruction, than to giue fiue pounds a yeer for other ordinary education.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſcham</hi> in like manner affirmeth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 2.</note> that <hi>Queene</hi> ELIZABETH, who neuer took yet Greek or La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Grammar in her hand (after the firſt declining of a Noun and a Verb) did in a yeer or two attaine to ſuch a perfect vnderſtanding in both Tongues, and to ſuch a ready vtterance of the Latine, and that with ſuch judgement; as they were few in number in both Vniuerſities, or elſewhere in <hi>England,</hi> that were in both Tongues comparable with her Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:20234:23"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Scaliger</hi> alſo, without any Grammar at all,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Th. Hain.</hi>
               </note> did come to an admired perfection in the Greek Tong. And other heer in <hi>England,</hi> more worthy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, are comne without any rules at all to many languages. Thus did <hi>Tib.</hi> and <hi>Ca. Gracchi:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. Ciceronia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. f.</hi> 10</note> thus did <hi>Laelia,</hi> the <hi>Mutiae</hi> and <hi>Luciniae:</hi> thus did <hi>Hortenſia,</hi> thus <hi>Curio,</hi> learn their eloquence: And thus, among the <hi>Craſsi,</hi> the <hi>Scipiones,</hi> the <hi>Mutij,</hi> and many other <hi>Roman Oraters</hi> before <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> the name and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of well-ſpeaking flouriſhed entire and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted: not by reaſon, art or ſcience; but onely by good Vſe, Cuſtome and conuerſation. And thus, and no otherwiſe, for aboue three thouſand yeers, were all languages learned; and ſo are ſtill, though in ſome places the Art of Grammar, with greater toil and leſſer profit, be imbraced.</p>
            <p>And that made <hi>Schorus</hi> ſay, Wee are perſwaded,
<note place="margin">In ſpecim. &amp;c.</note> that children may by imitation, example and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome (not onely come to ſpeak, but) be made bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Grammarians, Orators and Philoſophers, than by precepts.</p>
            <p>Now, if Cuſtome, ſaith <hi>Varro,</hi> be to be followed,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Analogia.</hi>
               </note> there is no need of precepts: for, if we follow Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, precepts will follow vs. And he ſpares not to confeſſe, that he cannot command the Cuſtome of the people; but their Cuſtome will command his: for, ſaith hee, whatſoeuer confuſed Cuſtome hath receiued, muſt and will paſſe without contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            <p>And that made <hi>Marcellus</hi> tell <hi>Tiberius Caeſar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tranquillus cis. a Zuing. Theat. l.</hi> 1.</note> that he could not make words, though hee could make
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20234:24"/>men, free of the City: and he gaue <hi>Capito</hi> the lie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1.13.</note> in <hi>Caeſars</hi> preſence. And this Cuſtome, and the change thereof, <hi>Quintilian</hi> acknowledgeth, not onely in ſpeech, but in Orthographie.</p>
            <p>The fruitleſſe endeauours alſo of many in our owne language, namely of <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Mulcaster</hi> (cited by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.
<note place="margin">Praef. Logon.</note> 
               <hi>Alex. Gill</hi>) make them acknowledge, that, after the loſs of much time &amp; paper, all muſt be remitted to the ſway of Cuſtom. And yet haue men of note, and the more noted for knowing thus much, once more endeauoured againſt their owne knowledge: which, I wonder at.</p>
            <p>Moreouer:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Or. l.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Cicero</hi> tels vs, that it is intolerable, in diſcourſe to forſake the ordinary forme of ſpeech, and the vſuall or common ſenſe of Cuſtome: for, Vſe of all other is the beſt Lord &amp; Maſter; which, ruling it ſelf by the judgement of the ear all ſpeech muſt be likewiſe ruled by it. And, ſaith he, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth vs, that ſuch, whether in proſe or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſie, are eſpecially to be commended, as, by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition or counterpoize of their words, bring plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to their Auditory, and by their ſentences doo teach them ſomething; yet ſo, that the peoples or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Vſe and Cuſtome be obſerued: for, Vſe &amp; Cuſtome are of that authority, that they transform antient languages, degrade words preſent, coyne new ones, and recall old ones at their pleaſure. And this made <hi>Horace</hi> ſay,
<note place="margin">Art. poet.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vt ſyluaefolijs pronos mutantur in annos,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prima cadunt: ita verborum vetus interitaetas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et invenum ritu florent, modo nata vigent<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:20234:24"/>
                  <l>As woods are chang'd in leaues by winters fall:</l>
                  <l>So words do change their age that's paſt recall,</l>
                  <l>And new-born youth-like flouriſh and top all.</l>
               </q> And then,
<note place="margin">Ib.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>—mortalia facta peribunt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nedum ſermonum ſtet honos &amp; gratia vivax.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Multa renaſcentur quae iam cecidere, cadent<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quae nunc ſunt in honore vocabula, ſi volet vſus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quem penes arbitrium eſt, &amp; ius, &amp; norma loquendi.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>—all mortall facts giue place:</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Much leſſe ſhould ſpeech keep it firſt praiſe and grace.</p>
            <p>Cuſtome brings words vnus'd, to Vſe; and ſuch,</p>
            <p>As are moſt vſuall, to diſpleaſe as much.</p>
            <p>The worth of ſpeech is judg'd by Cuſtomes touch.</p>
            <p>And this made <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> likewiſe affirm, that the latine Tongue proceeded not by Art, but by Vſe and Cuſtome.</p>
            <p>Thus wee may gather, that Art and Vſe are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt oppoſite: which,
<note place="margin">In Virgilianis expoſitionibus.</note> 
               <hi>Servius</hi> the Prince of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians plainly ratifies; telling vs often, that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie (which is nothing but the written Vſe or Cuſtome of antient Authors) doth confound Art. Whereof, <hi>Nonius Marcellus</hi> giues vs this Inſtance: All that haue followed Art, deny that we ought to adde a Prepoſition vnto Verbs: but the authoritie of th' Antients bids vs place it before them. And <hi>Servius</hi> giues vs another; ſaying, Art requires, that we ſhould not put a Prepoſition with the names of Cities, but with the reſt we ſhould: yet Authors,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20234:25"/>ſaith he, for the moſt part, vſe the contrary; and he citeth <hi>Cicero</hi> &amp; <hi>Virgil</hi> comprehending verſe as well as proſe; leſt Grammarians in Poets ſhould excuſe it with poeticall licence. And for this cauſe, <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian</hi> ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſt. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 4</note> The caſe is to bee altered, if that which wee beganne withall run harſhly. As if <hi>Quintilian</hi> ſhould ſay with <hi>Nonius Marcellus,</hi> The caſe, gender, tenſes, conjugations, declenſions, and all gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall collections, are to be altered if ſpeech ſound ill in pronunciation.: for, authority and experience tell vs, that we can neither in the Latine, nor in any other Tongue, be obedient vnto other rules or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, than Cuſtome and our ſenſe of hearing.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Badius</hi> affirmeth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Comment. ſuper Virg. in</hi> 1. <hi>Aeneidos.</hi>
               </note> that conſtruction is to bee ſometimes taken from the cuſtom of ſpeaking: for, if it be taken according to the rules of Grammari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, it is altogether diſpleaſing; in that it depriueth words of their dignity, and ſentences of their waight and grauity:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Analogia vid. Iul. C. Scal. de cauſ. ling. lat. l.</hi> 9. <hi>a.</hi> 161</note> and <hi>Varro</hi> concludes (what <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Scaliger</hi> confirmeth) There are many in this kinde, in which wee rather follow Cuſtome, than the reaſon of words.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, <hi>Hermannus Buſchius</hi> was not afraid to tell vs plainly, that it is a very childiſh and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous thing, eſpecially in one of mans eſtate, to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of nothing but of boyiſh rules; and to bee ſo beſotted in them, that hee houlds it a great offenſe to ſtep a nails breadth from the bounds that they haue limited; and to be altogether ignorant in the authority of the graueſt Writers, or deſpiſe it; and to accoſt rather trifling precepts, than th' approued
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20234:25"/>Authours of ſo many ages, on whom the latine Tongue depends, and lies as at anchor: for, wee muſt not ſpeak onely as wee are commanded by Grammar-rules; but rather altogether as moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Authours haue written. Makeſt thou any doubt of following that which <hi>Cicero, Varro, Livius, Florus, Valerius,</hi> and both the <hi>Plinij,</hi> and others of the pureſt Authors haue ſpoken? Do'ſt thou as yet imagine, that he that vſeth <hi>Cicero's</hi> &amp; <hi>Virgil's</hi> words, doth ſpeak improperly? Such as are inthrald to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexanders</hi> Grammar, reade in <hi>Virgil, Pars &amp; certare pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati. Pars ingenti ſubiere feretro. Pars ingentem formidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne turpi ſcandunt rurſus equum. O vir fortis at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> amicus clama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</hi> and thoſe that <hi>Quintilian</hi> produceth; which ſeem, ſaith he, and are not faulty; becauſe it is the cuſtome of ſpeaking amongſt Authors, as <hi>Tragaedia Thyeſtes, Ludi floralia &amp; Megaleſia,</hi> and the like. But, ſay they, we muſt not imitate this form of ſpeaking or writing; as if wee were neceſſarily tied like chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d rather the regular proceeding of ſom one word, than vnto the matter it ſelf. <hi>Donatus,</hi> on the Prologue of <hi>Adelphos</hi> in <hi>Terence,</hi> wrote, <hi>In A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphis Terentiana:</hi> but, if I ſhall ſay ſo, you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue me, and make me write, <hi>In Adelphis Terentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi> But I'le eſteem you but as a freſhman, or an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary ſcholar. If therefore you ſhall think <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma pars homines morem hunc habent,</hi> not to be rightly ſaid, becauſe the Grammar-rule hath, Two Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiues in one and the ſame caſe cannot be joyned without a Copula. [or, Two Subſtantiues cannot come together, betokening diuers things, vnleſſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20234:26"/>the later be put in the genitiue caſe] you are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Orat. pro</hi> C. <hi>Rab.</hi>
               </note> for, <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quid vociferabere, decem millia talenta Gabinio eſse promiſsa;</hi> and not, <hi>decem millia talen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum.</hi> And <hi>Livius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Et Philippei nummi aurei de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem quatuor millia, vigintiquatuor;</hi> and not, <hi>aureorum nummorum millia quatuordecim, &amp;c.</hi> Wherefore, ſaith hee, I bouldly affirm, that the latine Tongue is not to be ſought-for out of rules or Gammars, but out of Authors.</p>
            <p>Thus it appeareth (ſaith <hi>Cominius</hi>) that <hi>Herman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Buſchius</hi> allowes of all that I haue written of this ſubiect, and confirmes it.</p>
            <p>For firſt he perceiu'd, and prou'd, that ancient Authors ſpake neither by Art, nor by the rules of Grammar. Next, that he that will follow Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar or her rules, muſt of neceſsitie deſpiſe <hi>Orators, Poets,</hi> and other ancient Authors: whereby he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, that the precepts of this Art, and the vſe of the Ancients are contrarie: and that we ſhould not ſpeak according to the rules of Art, but according to the cuſtome of Antients. Then, that it is a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh thing to be afraid to follow the ſpeech of the Ancients. And that Grammarians co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand things contrarie. For they iudge <hi>Terence, Virgil, Cicero,</hi> and the like to be the eleganteſt Writers: and yet they prohibit our imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them in many things;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>c. de dat. &amp; abl. plur. prima decl.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Priſcianus</hi> himſelfe, where (he ſaith) the ancient Authors are found to haue written many things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt rule, vitiouſly, both in theſe and in other ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>c. de dat. &amp; abl. pl.</hi> 2 <hi>a. decl.</hi>
               </note> wherein they are not to be imitated. And in another place, he intimates the contrarie: as, that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20234:26"/>we ought to knowe the reaſon of Analogie; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to follow the cuſtome of Authors. And a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before, hee ſayth; There are ſome Nounes whoſe caſes are not all in vſe: which though wee may by Analogie produce; yet becauſe wee finde them not in Authors, I hold they ought to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed. No man can deny but theſe are diuers and contrarie. And then, this <hi>Buſchius</hi> teacheth that the antient Authors very often bring many things againſt the rules of Grammarians; wherefore it is moſt certaine, that theſe neither wrote, nor ſpake by this Art. Which <hi>Nonius Marcellus</hi> ſheweth, and proueth by innumerable examples. And it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that the firſt and later Grammarians are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. For they drewe their Art out of ancient Authors, and went about to proue it out of their authoritie. Again: it followes that others were yet more deceiued, that excuſe the cuſtome of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, by figures, poetical licence, and other Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall inuentions; whereas they finde that theſe ancient Authors neither knew them, nor obſerued them.</p>
            <p>And in concluſion, he affirmes the Latine Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is not to be ſought by Art, but out of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors. And it manifeſtly appeares that there are two kindes of Latine; one naturall, the other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterate. The naturall is that which the men of authority amongſt the Romans, the Nobilitie, and that which almoſt all men ſpake, and wherein the ancient Authors <hi>Cicero</hi> and the reſt did write; in which are the pleaſures of the language, true elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20234:27"/>all delight &amp; perfect elegancy; who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed their works by no Art of Grammar, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Vſe and Cuſtome of ſpeaking, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the judgement of hearing.
<note place="margin">In perf. Or.</note> And therefore <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid, Our Anceſters thought good, that we ſhould obey Cuſtome, linked with the judgement of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: for, Cuſtome hath giuen leaue, that it ſhall be lawfull to offend for ſweetnes ſake. Yet Cuſtom permitteth, that wee ſhould produce ſomething which the common people ſpeak not; but not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be for ſweetnes ſake, the pleaſure of the ear, and to vtter thoſe things which haue better ſound than others; and in pronouncing, fal better, without offenſe to Vſe and Cuſtome. And this is that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence which the Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marians call poeticall Lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: which they think to be giuen onely vnto Poets, to help the meaſure of their Verſes; and doe not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that it is as well giuen vnto <hi>Orators, Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Philoſophers,</hi> and all other whatſoeuer, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their inclination or election. And of this licence, onely Grammar doth defraud vs; nay, it doth confound and drown it. And this begets that other latine Tongue which is adulterate, and daily depraued with new rules and precepts; and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volued and intricate, that how thou ſhould'ſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reade, write or ſpeak, ſaith he, thou knoweſt not. And this almoſt euery man perceiues, that hath betaken himſelf to reading of antient Authors, and begins but to taſte their elegancie: And this, ſhould euery man of wiſdome look vnto. For, there is no diligence or ſubtilty, ſaith he, that can bring vs to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20234:27"/>the latin elega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, vnleſs we abſolutely ſo renounce Grammar, that wee doe not regard ſo much as the leaſt rule thereof; but onely rely vpon the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and pleaſure of the eare, and ſpeak after Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, ſo far as it is limited by antient Authors. And thus without any toil we ſhall bee eloquent. For, Grammar is ſo far from beeing the foundation of the latine Tongue (or any other); that it is rather the greateſt hinderance therein, and cauſe of all the errors &amp; contentions that daily riſe among Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians: As it is alſo in my judgement, ſaith hee, the main root, fountain and beginning of all barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme. Nor finde I other out of <hi>Varro, Cicero, Plinie, Quintilian.,</hi> or other antient Orators or Poets. And whoſoeuer ſhall be led by it, will be deceiued, and neuer come to elegancy, either in this or any other languages.</p>
            <p>But, notwithſtanding all theſe reaſons, all theſe experiments, all theſe graue and waighty teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; I doubt not, but I ſhall heare of ſome <hi>Demetri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> who with his Aſſociats, to keep vp the trade, wil ſtill be crying, <hi>Magna Diana Epheſiorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, I appeal to thee, my <hi>Defendreſs,</hi> and to thy Tribunall; moſt humbly imploring no other redreſſe of injurious oppreſſions, but that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of thy ſelf, <hi>O Truth,</hi> may be ſo much reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that <hi>blinde-fould Opinion, Patroneſſe of Grammar and Grammarians,</hi> may ceaſe to gouern and to keep the people (as her ſelf is) hood-winkt: And that, vpon thy ſtraight and imperiall Command, ſhee may leaue all men indifferent, and in the poſture of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20234:28"/>an equall balance, readie to turn, where reaſon, ſenſe and demonſtration are moſt ponderous.</p>
            <p>And the waking part of Students ſhall not onely acknowledge thy diuine &amp; powerfull hand in the cure of their deplored lethargie: but my ſelfe, thy deuote ſuppliant, in <hi>lieu</hi> thereof ſhall bee obliged in my next endeuours, to diſcouer in what manner this <hi>vſe, Cuſtome,</hi> and <hi>Authoritie</hi> ſhould be ſought and ordered, for the ſpeedie, cheape, eaſy, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible furniſhing of this, and euery other Nation, with all ſorts of pureſt Languages.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faultes eſcaped, in ſome Copies.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Pag.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Line</cell>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>28.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Thenth,</hi> read <hi>Theuth.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>30.</cell>
                     <cell>this in that <hi>reade</hi> that in this.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23.</cell>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Liuius, Andronicus,</hi> reade <hi>Liuius Andronicus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</cell>
                     <cell>been found <hi>reade</hi> been hitherto found.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20234:28"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
